<?xml version="1.0" encoding="US-ASCII"?>
<!DOCTYPE rfc SYSTEM "rfc2629.dtd">
<?rfc toc="yes"?>
<?rfc tocompact="yes"?>
<?rfc tocdepth="3"?>
<?rfc tocindent="yes"?>
<?rfc symrefs="yes"?>
<?rfc sortrefs="yes"?>
<?rfc comments="no"?>
<?rfc inline="yes"?>
<?rfc compact="yes"?>
<?rfc subcompact="no"?>
<rfc xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"  category="std" docName="draft-ietf-raviolli-trusted-domain-srv6"
     ipr="trust200902"
     obsoletes="" submissionType="IETF" updates="" xml:lang="en">
    <front>
        <title abbrev="draft-ietf-raviolli-trusted-domain-srv6">
            Trusted Domain SRv6
        </title>

        <author fullname="Andrew Alston" initials="A." surname="Alston">
            <organization>Liquid Intelligent Technologies</organization>
            <address>
                <email>andrew-ietf@liquid.tech
                </email>
                <uri/>
            </address>
        </author>
        <author fullname="Tom Hill" initials="T." surname="Hill">
            <organization>British Telecom</organization>
            <address>
                <email>tom.2.hill@bt.com
                </email>
                <uri/>
            </address>
        </author>
        <author fullname="Tony Przygienda" initials="A." surname="Przygienda">
            <organization>Juniper</organization>
            <address>
                <postal>
                    <street>1137 Innovation Way
                    </street>
                    <city>Sunnyvale</city>
                    <region>CA
                    </region>
                    <code/>
                    <country>USA
                    </country>
                </postal>
                <phone/>
                <facsimile/>
                <email>prz@juniper.net
                </email>
                <uri/>
            </address>
        </author>
        <date year="2023"/>
        <abstract>
            <t>
            </t>
        </abstract>
        <note title="Requirements Language">
            <t>The key words "MUST", "MUST NOT", "REQUIRED", "SHALL", "SHALL NOT",
                "SHOULD", "SHOULD NOT", "RECOMMENDED", "MAY", and "OPTIONAL" in this
                document are to be interpreted as described in <xref format="default"
                                                                     pageno="false" target="RFC2119">RFC 2119</xref>.
            </t>
        </note>
    </front>
    <middle>

        <section title="Glossary" >
            <dl newline="true" spacing="normal">

            <dt>Fail-Closed Domain:</dt>
            <dd>
                synonymous with a Trusted Domain.
            </dd>

            <dt>
                Trusted Domain:
            </dt>
            <dd>
                A domain that prevents processing of a protocol without explicit configuration, defined
                in detail in <xref target="fcpd"/>.
            </dd>
            </dl>

        </section>

        <section title="Description" >
            <t>
                 SRv6 as designed has interest from various sectors, though is deployment is being limited by the fact that
                 there are known security problems in the protocol design. This document specifies a standard to create a
                 solution that closes some of the major security concerns, while retaining the basis of the SRv6 protocol.
            </t>
        </section>

        <section title="The SRv6 Security Problem">
            <t>
                SRv6 relies in its architecture on the concept of limited domain which is too vague
                a concept to form a solid security base.
            </t>
            <t>
                Limited domains that fail open, can, and will, invariably leak beyond the domain due to human error. 
            </t>
            <t>
                As per <xref format="default" pageno="false" target="RFC8402">RFC 8402</xref>RFC8402 Section 8, 
                SRv6 that leaks beyond the border of a trusted domain creates a security violation.
            </t>
            <t>
                The solution is to create a trusted domain that has a default fail-closed approach.
            </t>
            <t> Exmaples of fail closed protocols currently include:</t>
            <ul>
                <li>mpls</li>
                <li>clns</li>
                <li>llpd</li>
                <li>bier</li>
            </ul>
        </section>

        <section title="Characteristics of a Fail-Closed Protocol Domain" anchor="fcpd">
            <t>
                A fail closed protocol domain is determined by following properties:
            </t>
            <t>
                    Processing of the protocol packet on an interface requires explicit configuration with a
                default drop behavior.</t>
                <t>
                    Leaking of protocol packets beyond the boundary of fail-closed domain requires
                    explicit config.
                </t>
                <t>
                    Fail closed protocols must be identifiable by their top level (e.g. link layer) encoding.
                </t>
                <t>
                    Classification of the protocol must be deterministic.
                </t>
                <t>
                    Confining the protocol to the trusted domaim must not require complex processing in
                    either hardware or software, so as to allow for scalability.
                </t>
                <t>
                    The boundary of a trusted domain consists of a set of interfaces that exhibit default
                    behavior.
                </t>
        </section>
         
         <section title="SRv6 in the context of a trusted domain - an objective analysis">
              <t>
                   It is currently impossible to differentiate SRv6 and IPv6 at the link-layer
              </t>
              <t>
                   In the event of a frame being sent into a trusted domain, either accidently or by a malicious actor,
                   it is possible to send the frame to a node binding the specific SID, and have the packet processed,
                   irrespective of the content of the underlying (encapsulated) frame
              </t>
              <t>
                   The current security proposals in RFC8402 section 8.2, security is based on the application of
                   filters preventing ingress traffic at the boundary routers destined towards a SID within the domain.
                   Such filtering is prone to configuration errors and in addition, has significant impact on TCAM utilization 
                   on devices that have large numbers of ingress points into the domain
              </t>
              <t> 
                   In the context of a trusted domain, anything outside of the operators control should not be considered
                   trusted.  This means applying filters to prevent leakage into the domain at every customer port,
                   every server, and every cloud stack.  Any lapse in the filters can cause grevious harm
              </t>
         </section>
         
         <section title="Trusted-Domain Implementation">
              <t>
                   To implement SRv6 in the context of a trusted domain, it is necessary to create a fail-closed scenario.
                   To do this, requires modification of the protoccol at both the boundary routers and the transit nodes
              </t>
              <section title="Boundary routers">
                   <t>
                        Trusted Domain boundary routers form the point at which the new ethertype is imposed.
                        Imposition of the ethertype happens on packet ingress, at the same point as SRv6 header imposition
                        is performed.
                   </t>
                   <t>
                        Boundary interfaces will, by default, drop packets already containing the srv6-td ethertype.
                   </t>
              </section>
              <section title="Transit routers">
                   <t>
                        In the case of a transit router, should a frame not be marked with the srv6-td ethertype, the
                        frame will be treated as a standard IPv6 packet for the purposes of handling and forwarding.
                   </t>
                   <t>
                        Only frames marked with the srv6-td ethertype will be processed as SRv6 packets
                   </t>
                   <t>
                        A router configured for TD-SRv6 MUST drop packets containing an SRH in the absense of the srv6-td 
                        ethertype.
                   </t>
              </section>
         </section>
              

        <section anchor="registry" title="Registry Considerations">
            <section anchor="IANA" title="IANA Considerations" toc="default">

                <t>
                     No IANA Considerations
                </t>
            </section>

            <section anchor="IEEE" title="IEEE Considerations" toc="default">
                <t>
                     TD-SRv6 Ethertype: TBD0
                </t>

            </section>

        </section>

        <section title="Security Considerations">
            <t>
                 This draft enhances the security mechanisms required by section 8 of RFC8402, and does not
                 impose any further security considerations of its own.
            </t>
        </section>

       <section title="Contributors">
            <t>
                 Weiqiang Cheng 
            </t>
            <t> 
                 chengweiqiang@chinamobile.com
            </t>
         </section>

    </middle>
    <back>
        <references title="Informative References">

        </references>
        <references title="Normative References">
            <xi:include href="https://xml2rfc.tools.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.2119.xml"/>
            <xi:include href="https://xml2rfc.tools.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.8402.xml"/>

        </references>

    </back>
</rfc>
