<?xml version="1.0" encoding="US-ASCII"?>
<!DOCTYPE rfc SYSTEM "rfc2629.dtd">
<?rfc toc="yes"?>
<?rfc tocompact="yes"?>
<?rfc tocdepth="3"?>
<?rfc tocindent="yes"?>
<?rfc symrefs="yes"?>
<?rfc sortrefs="yes"?>
<?rfc comments="no"?>
<?rfc inline="yes"?>
<?rfc compact="yes"?>
<?rfc subcompact="no"?>
<rfc xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"  category="std" docName="draft-ietf-raviolli-trusted-domain-srv6"
     ipr="trust200902"
     obsoletes="" submissionType="IETF" updates="" xml:lang="en">
    <front>
        <title abbrev="draft-ietf-raviolli-trusted-domain-srv6">
            Trusted Domain SRv6
        </title>

        <author fullname="Andrew Alston" initials="A." surname="Alston">
            <organization>Liquid Intelligent Technologies</organization>
            <address>
                <email>andrew-ietf@liquid.tech
                </email>
                <uri/>
            </address>
        </author>
        <author fullname="Tom Hill" initials="T." surname="Hill">
            <organization>British Telecom</organization>
            <address>
                <email>tom.2.hill@bt.com
                </email>
                <uri/>
            </address>
        </author>
        <author fullname="Tony Przygienda" initials="A." surname="Przygienda">
            <organization>Juniper</organization>
            <address>
                <postal>
                    <street>1137 Innovation Way
                    </street>
                    <city>Sunnyvale</city>
                    <region>CA
                    </region>
                    <code/>
                    <country>USA
                    </country>
                </postal>
                <phone/>
                <facsimile/>
                <email>prz@juniper.net
                </email>
                <uri/>
            </address>
        </author>
        <date year="2023"/>
        <abstract>
            <t>
            </t>
        </abstract>
        <note title="Requirements Language">
            <t>The key words "MUST", "MUST NOT", "REQUIRED", "SHALL", "SHALL NOT",
                "SHOULD", "SHOULD NOT", "RECOMMENDED", "MAY", and "OPTIONAL" in this
                document are to be interpreted as described in <xref format="default"
                                                                     pageno="false" target="RFC2119">RFC 2119</xref>.
            </t>
        </note>
    </front>
    <middle>



        <section title="Description" >
            <t>
                 SRv6 as designed has evoked interest from various parties,
                though its deployment is being limited by known security problems
                in its architecture. This document specifies a standard to create a
                 solution that closes some of the major security concerns,
                while retaining the basis of the SRv6 protocol.
            </t>
        </section>

        <section title="Glossary" >
            <dl newline="true" spacing="normal">

                <dt>Fail-Closed Domain:</dt>
                <dd>
                    synonymous with a Trusted Domain.
                </dd>

                <dt>
                    Trusted Domain (TD):
                </dt>
                <dd>
                    A domain that prevents processing of a protocol without explicit configuration, defined
                    in detail in <xref target="fcpd"/>.
                </dd>

                <dt>
                    Fail-Closed Protocol (FPC):
                </dt>
                <dd>
                    A protocol that can be deployed by establishing a fail closed domain.
                </dd>

                <dt>
                    TD-SRv6:
                </dt>
                <dd>
                    SRv6 modified to become a FPC and with that allowing for easy deployment in
                    a TD.
                </dd>
            </dl>

        </section>

        <section title="The SRv6 Security Problem">
            <t>
                SRv6 relies in its architecture on the concept of limited domain which
                as a concept suffers from lack of security that is deployable in
                economical, scalable fashion easily.
            </t>
            <t>
                Limited domains without very careful deployment will invariably leak beyond
                the domain and allow untrusted traffic to enter the domain and terminate
                on any arbitrary node.
            </t>
            <t>
                As
                per <xref format="default" pageno="false" target="RFC8402">RFC 8402</xref>RFC8402 Section 8,
                SRv6 that leaks beyond the border of a trusted domain creates a security violation.
            </t>
            <t>
                The proper solution is to create a trusted
                domain that has a default fail-closed approach and a well-defined
                red-black boundary.
            </t>
            <t> Examples of fail closed protocols currently include:</t>
            <ul>
                <li>mpls</li>
                <li>clns</li>
                <li>lldp</li>
                <li>bier</li>
            </ul>
        </section>

        <section title="Characteristics of a Fail-Closed Protocol Domain" anchor="fcpd">
            <t>
                A fail closed protocol domain is determined by following properties:
            </t>
            <t>
                    Processing of the protocol packet on an interface requires explicit configuration with a
                default drop behavior.</t>
                <t>
                    Leaking according protocol packets beyond the boundary of fail-closed domain requires
                    explicit config.
                </t>
                <t>
                    Fail closed protocols are easily identifiable by their top level
                    (e.g. link layer) encoding
                    early in the packet formats and often by fields at fixed offset.
                    In another words either their encoding or encapsulation allows to
                    distinguish it easily from other traffic.
                </t>
                <t>
                    Classification of the protocol packets is completely deterministic.
                </t>
                <t>
                    Confining the protocol to the trusted domaim does not require complex processing in
                    either hardware or software to allow for scalability and economical deployment.
                </t>
                <t>
                    The boundary of a trusted domain consists of a set of interfaces that exhibit default
                    behavior.
                </t>
        </section>
         
         <section title="SRv6 in the context of a trusted domain - an objective analysis">
              <t>
                   It is currently impossible to differentiate SRv6 and IPv6 at the link-layer or
                   easily at network layer by e.g. a reserved protocol number as IPSec does.
              </t>
              <t>
                   In the event of a packet being sent into a trusted domain, either accidentally
                  or by a malicious actor,
                   it is possible to send the frame to a node binding the specific SID,
                  and have the packet processed,
                   irrespective of the content of the underlying (encapsulated) packet.
              </t>
              <t>
                   The current security proposals in RFC8402 section 8.2, security is
                  based on the application of
                   filters preventing ingress traffic at the boundary routers destined
                  towards a SID within the domain.
                   Such filtering is prone to configuration errors and in addition,
                  has significant impact on TCAM utilization
                   on devices that have large numbers of ingress points into the domain.
                  The matching itself, due to the complexity and numerous possibilities
                  of expressing a set of SIDs will likely necessitate a complete semantic
                  parsing of such list to guarantee fully precise matching including
                  wildcarding in different forms.

              </t>
              <t> 
                   In the context of a trusted domain, anything outside of the
                  operators control should not be considered
                   trusted.  This means applying filters to prevent
                  leakage into the domain at every customer port,
                   every server, and every cloud stack.
                  The scale and complexity of maintaining such a "shorewall" is daunting
                  and at large scale will not be likely to keep up with the
                  timing necessary in case of attacks mounted and metamorphosing in
                  short time intervals. An attack avoiding the filter wall may evade
                  discovery for a long time in case of lack of sophisticated
                  traffic analyis and analytics tools.
              </t>
         </section>
         
         <section title="Trusted-Domain Implementation">
              <t>
                   To implement SRv6 in the context of a trusted domain, it is necessary
                  to modify it to allow deployment in a fail-closed boundary efficiently.
                   This requires changes to the protocol encapsulation at both the boundary
                  routers and the transit nodes.
                  This document introduces a distinct ethertype to be used for td-srv6
              </t>
              <section title="Boundary routers">
                   <t>
                        Trusted Domain boundary routers form the point at which the new
                       ethertype is imposed.
                        Imposition of the ethertype happens on packet ingress,
                       at the same point as SRv6 header imposition
                        is performed.
                   </t>
                   <t>
                        Boundary interfaces will, by default behavior, drop packets already
                       containing the srv6-td ethertype.
                   </t>
              </section>
              <section title="Transit and egress routers">
                   <t>
                        In the case of a transit or egress router, should a frame not
                       be marked with the srv6-td ethertype, the
                        frame will be treated as a standard IPv6 packet for the
                       purposes of handling and forwarding.
                   </t>
                   <t>
                        Only frames marked with the srv6-td ethertype will be
                       processed as SRv6 packets.
                   </t>
                   <t>
                        A router configured to process TD-SRv6 MUST drop packets
                       containing an SRH if received on any ethertype except srv6-td.
                   </t>
              </section>
         </section>
              

        <section anchor="registry" title="Registry Considerations">
            <section anchor="IANA" title="IANA Considerations" toc="default">

                <t>
                     No IANA Considerations
                </t>
            </section>

            <section anchor="IEEE" title="IEEE Considerations" toc="default">
                <t>
                     TD-SRv6 Ethertype: TBD0
                </t>

            </section>

        </section>

        <section title="Security Considerations">
            <t>
                 This draft enhances the security mechanisms required by section 8 of RFC8402, and does not
                 impose any further security considerations of its own.
            </t>
        </section>

       <section title="Contributors">
            <t>
                 Weiqiang Cheng 
            </t>
            <t> 
                 chengweiqiang@chinamobile.com
            </t>
         </section>

    </middle>
    <back>
        <references title="Informative References">

        </references>
        <references title="Normative References">
            <xi:include href="https://xml2rfc.tools.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.2119.xml"/>
            <xi:include href="https://xml2rfc.tools.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.8402.xml"/>

        </references>

    </back>
</rfc>
